Guide to the Richard Gamble Knight Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard Gamble Knight papers
1952-2003
MS 1999
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.09
(9 boxes)
The papers comprise images captured during Richard Gamble Knight's tenure from 1957 to 1961 as an employee of the architectural firm Eero Saarinen and Associates, and during other periods of Knight's life, such as his student years. Consisting of photographic prints, negatives, and slides, the images range from projects designed by Saarinen and Associates (including Dulles International Airport, John Deere and Company, Trans World Flight Center, and CBS Building in New York), to candid shots of Saarinen and his employees at work and socializing, to photographic studies of architectural forms and details. Also included in the papers are audio recordings of interviews Knight conducted with five former Saarinen employees for his book, Saarinen's Quest: A Memoir, published in 2008.
Knight, Richard Gamble
Arrangement
The records are arranged in two series: I. Images: prints, negatives, and slides, circa 1952-circa 1979. II. Interviews conducted for Saarinen's Quest: A Memoir, 2001-2003.
Scope and Contents
The papers comprise images captured during Richard Gamble Knight's tenure from 1957 to 1961 as an employee of the architectural firm Eero Saarinen and Associates, and during other periods of Knight's life, such as his student years. Consisting of photographic prints, negatives, and slides, the images range from projects designed by Saarinen and Associates (including Dulles International Airport, John Deere and Company, Trans World Flight Center, CBS Building in New York, and Morse and Stiles Colleges at Yale University), to candid shots of Saarinen and his employees at work and socializing, to photographic studies of architectural forms and details. Also included in the papers are audio recordings of interviews Knight conducted with five former Saarinen employees for his book, Saarinen's Quest: A Memoir, published in 2008.
Related Materials
Eero Saarinen Collection (MS 593).
Biographical / Historical
Born in Flint, Michigan, on November 29, 1926, Richard Gamble Knight studied engineering and architecture at the University of Michigan (BS Engineering, 1951), the Cranbrook Academy of Art, and Lawrence Technical University (BS Architecture, 1957) in Southfield, Michigan. In 1957, Knight was hired as a junior architectural designer at Eero Saarinen and Associates in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, where he worked until Saarinen's death in 1961. A budding photographer as well as an architect, Knight succeeded Balthazar Korab as the firm's "court photographer," documenting the design process for clients and creating a visual record of the firm's activities and creative output. After Saarinen's death in 1961, Knight continued his career as an architect, and also took on roles as a graphic and interior designer, an instructor of design, a writer, and a prolific multimedia artist whose works were exhibited regularly. In 2008, Knight published Saarinen's Quest: A Memoir (San Francisco: William Stout Publishers), which focuses on Knight's time at Eero Saarinen and Associates, and features many of the photographs Knight took while employed at the firm. Knight died on December 16, 2008, in Alameda, California.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Judith Ann Lynch, 2013.
Architecture -- 20th Century -- United States; Architecture, American -- 20th Century; Architecture, Modern -- 20th Century; Architectural drawings (visual works); Architectural records; Knight, Richard Gamble; Pelli, Cesar; Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961; CBS Building (New York, N.Y.); Trans World Airlines Terminal (New York, N.Y.)
- Images: prints, negatives, and slides, Circa 1952-circa 1979; Series I
  - Projects
    - General contact sheets, Circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Images of the CBS Building, Jefferson National Expansion Memorial (St. Louis Gateway Arch), TWA terminal in New York, U.S. Embassy in London, and Yale University's Morse and Stiles residential colleges and the David Ingalls Rink.
    - Bell Labs, Holmdel, New Jersey, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - CBS Building, New York, New York, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dulles International Airport, Washington D.C., 1959-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - General Motors Technical Center, Warren, Michigan, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - International Business Machines (IBM), Rochester, Minnesotta, and Yorktown, New York, 1958-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Jefferson National Expansion Museum, St. Louis, Missouri, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      General
      This project is commonly referred to as the St. Louis Gateway Arch.
    - John Deere and Company Administrative Headquarters, Moline, Illinois, 1958-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) Chapel and Kresge Auditorium, Cambridge, Massachusetts, Circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miller, J. Irwin, residence, Columbus, Indiana, Circa 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Milwaukee County War Memorial, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, Circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - North Christian Church, Columbus, Indiana, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Trans World Flight Center (TWA Terminal 5), JFK Airport, New York, New York, 1958-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - United States Embassy, London, England, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - United States Embassy, Oslo, Norway, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - University of Pennsylvania, Women's Residence Hall, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, New York, Circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Vivian Beaumont Repertory Theater and Library Museum, New York, New York, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut
      - David S. Ingalls Hockey Rink, Circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - New Colleges (Samuel F. B. Morse and Ezra Stiles Colleges), 1959-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 5-9)
  - Eero Saarinen and Associates
    - Bloomfield Hills office, Circa 1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Eero Saarinen candid shots, Circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Office life, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Office party (for Tony Lumsden?), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Office staff for scale figures, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Saarinen house, Circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Personal
    Unidentified images in this series may have been projects Knight pursued as a student.
    - Backgrounds, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Drawings, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Furniture, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Graphics and artwork, unidentified, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Illustrations for Saarinen's Quest: A Memoir, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Jane Knight fiber art, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous architectural detail, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Models, unidentified, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - People, unidentified, 1960s? (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - School projects, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Sculpture and pottery, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Texture studies, Circa 1952-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Interviews conducted for Saarinen's Quest: A Memoir, 2001-2003; Series II
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Knorr, Don, 2001 October 16; 1 (Box 3)
  - Paulsen, Glen, 2002 August 8; 2 (Box 4–5)
  - Pelli, Cesar, 2003 June 2; 1 (Box 6)
    Interview at his office, 1056 Chapel Street, New Haven, Connecticut.
  - Pudists, Ruth Clements, 2002 August 12; 2 (Box 7–8)
  - Roth, Harold, 2003 May 31; 1 (Box 9)
    Interview at his office, Roth & Moore Architects, 65 Audubon Street, New Haven, Connecticut.